{
  "reference_number": "11762",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a goal to reach net zero emissions by the second half of the century and the Climate Change Commission advises on the specific target for the Government to set later",
      "answer_index": 11,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Long-Lived Gases and Stabilised Short-Lived Gases - Long-lived gases to net zero by 2050 while also stabilising short-lived gases",
      "answer_index": 12,
      "notes": "Short lived gases are fueled to a greater or lesser degree by intensive dairying and the overuse or urea. Going back to a clover-based\n source of nitrogen and reducing animal numbers to the carrying capacity of the soil need to be immediate steps."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "We need to undertake practical projects that actually reduce domestic emissions. No entity should be absolved of it's responsibilities\n\n by being able to offset emissions by buying overseas carbon credits."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "It would make sense to have the ability to revise targets if opportunities arise which enabled us to speed up the process and reduce\n the time line."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The ability to select the 'low-hanging fruit' such as tree planting , energy efficiency, increased public transport, coastal shipping,\n increased rail use for passengers as well as freight, import substitution, and other low carbon initiatives in the first five years, buys\n time to work through the next two stages to ensure systems are set up to meet the 2050 target."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - the third emissions budget should be able to be changed but only when the subsequent budget is set",
      "answer_index": 4,
      "notes": "Bi-partisan agreement between all Political Parties is essential from the outset, and any changes must be ratified by the Government\n of the day following meaningful consultation of all interested Governmental and non-Governmental groups."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I have not read the Discussion Document but the principle is sound. Again, there needs to be a general consensus before the\nbudget is finalised."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes, it is five minutes to Midnight. We do not have the luxury of procrastination."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "All sectors need to work with the Government. The Agriculture Sector needs to implement practical projects to offset it's emissions,\nsuch as planting appropriate tree species or protecting native areas, with assistance from Government for fencing materials. The\n\nequivalent of 10 percent of any farm planted in trees (or equivalent) is sufficient to offset the farm's carbon footprint according to a\nMinistry of Forestry report of some years ago. Carbon credits could be the reward for agricultural carbon sequestration initiatives that\nare permanent. The agricultural sector should be prepared to pay a carbon tax on fuel in line with all other groups and individuals."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Again, without having read the document I can see the sense in the Commission having this function. It may also be helpful for the\n\nCommission to have a reference group made up of environmental groups to liase with."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The level of expertise in the sciences would be essential, also social policy, communication skills and lateral thinking! Again, a\n\ncarefully chosen reference group could support the Commission."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes, as adaptation will be one of the strategies required to cope with changed conditions in the future."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "It is essential that organisations declare their concerns in order to future proof them. Insurance companies will have a major role in\n\nshaping our society, as will Banks, for instance."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "New Zealanders are a practical people. I would hope that moving into a low carbon economy will be the catalyst for a sustainable\n\nfuture where Climate Change is at the forefront of planning. The Government can play an important role in leading by example. For\ninstance, purchasing wool for carpets and insulation in all Government buildings, enacting legislation to require packaging to be fit for\n\npurpose, restoring rivers dammed for electricity to ecosystem health, introducing progressive power pricing, ensuring education for\nlife, maintaining the Predator Free initiative- which also assists native forest carbon sequestration, restoration of rail passenger\n\nservices for the South island, emphasis on rainwater harvest rather than aquifer mining, assistance with funding for regional upgrades\nof wastewater facilities, and an emphasis on value-added rather than an economy based on commodities. Taking the pressure of our\nnatural world must be part of our Climate change policy. I am much heartened by the determination of so many to make positive\n\nchanges for the sake of our Planet and future generations. Thank you for the opportunity to submit to this Proposal."
    }
  ]
}
